[Music]
Stanford
University this is Sanjay thank did we
get Sanjay on the on record recorded yes
okay so we just want to announce that uh
we're trying to collect of all the old
lectures the video lectures that are on
YouTube in one kind of a collection and
the idea is for everybody who's taking
classes online and offline we can
actually have a easy way to navigate
through all the lectures if you have to
hunt for them right right so we're
passing out a little sheet that's got a
web address on it right now this is a
temporary housing for it and it should
be good until whenever um but when we do
get a final home we'll have a link
that'll directly go to it as well so
this link should be good for hopefully
all the tney until we hit Horizon and
all that good stuff all right okay
so this is the address let's see
HTTP colon SL SL new packet tech one
word new packet.com
SL
resources
susin that's the
address
where it's sort of the website for the
class so will be the website for the
class and um it's for anybody Outside
Inside where they can easily access
without all the confusion that's taking
place up till now easily access all of
the lectures that are online all
right we uh we have been discussing a
simple Quantum field and we're not
finished with it I have to take a 2-year
course and believe me a real course in
Quantum field theory is genuinely two
years of work it really cannot be done
in one year sensibly I have to take that
two years of quantum field Theory and
condense it down to a couple of Le
lectures we've already taken a couple of
lectures but uh I think we've had some
Forward
Motion I want to take the very very
simple version of a Quantum field that
we've already discussed well first of
all remind you what it is and discuss
how it is used again to describe
particle processes we've done a bit of
this we've talked a bit about how the
quantum field can code or um
cify scattering processes or creation
and Annihilation processes of particles
but I want to go into it in just a
little more
depth so that you can see where some of
the uh really interesting aspects of
quantum field Theory come
from and
how they influence questions like energy
conservation momentum conservation how
do those things how are they um related
to these Quantum fields that we've
discussed okay before I do so we need a
little bit of mathematics a little bit
of formal mathematics not much it's
mathematics that we've done before in
these series of classes but I want to
get them up on the
Blackboard uh the first thing is the
direct Delta function all right the
direct Delta function just to remind you
what it is
is
a
function which is the sort of a limit of
a genuine real function it's a function
of let's say it's coordinate let's for
the moment just call this coordinate uh
anything it could be X it could be K
let's just call it y so that we don't
Prejudice whether it's something that
I've called the that I've defined
previously the direct Delta function is
a function which is a sort of lump it's
concentrated
someplace it's concentrated someplace
and not other places but it's the limit
of an infinitely
sharply uh concentrated
function so we imagine that we can go to
a limit where this lump like function is
infinitely
narrow now I can't draw it as infinitely
narrow so I'll draw it with finite width
but imagine in your mind narrowing it
narrowing and narrowing it now of course
if you narrow it without raising its
height the area under it will decrease
and decrease and decrease to the point
where there's no area left under it so
what I want to do is to keep the area
under this function fixed as I decrease
the width so as I decrease the width I'm
going to raise up the height of it in
such a way that the product of height
time time width stays
constant how constant one just one an
area of one located someplace infinitely
narrow that's called a direct Delta
function if this point is y equals let's
call it a just uh to locate the
particular point then the direct Delta
function is Delta of y -
A and Delta of y - A is zero whenever y
does not equal a over here or over here
and equals something infinitely sharply
peaked at y equals a that's the direct
Delta
function and it has the property by
definition that the area under it the
deriv the integral with respect to Y is
one so it's so narrow and so high that
the area is one and it's it's
concentrated at the point where the
argument of the function is equal to
zero in other words when y equals a
that's the direct Delta
function okay now I want to show you how
the direct Delta function emerges from a
certain
integral an integral that we will come
on many many
times let's take the function e to the I
KX k oops e to the i
k
x now again as we discussed last time
we're discussing this on an
interval which is a a periodic
interval which has total length all
around it equal to l so the distance
around
here is equal to l i don't know if
this just the distance around it is
equal to
l it's periodic and so functions that
live on this periodic space here should
be periodic meaning to say they should
come back to themselves after one full
loop
okay
now what is K first of all K is one of
the allowed
values of wave number on the this in
other words one of the values of K where
e to the I KX is periodic so let's
assume an allowed value there and let's
take this function and integrate it over
the
entire
cyclic X Dimension here we could take X
going from 0 to L or for symmetry I
could take it to go from minus l/ 2 to
l/2 in other words instead inad of
starting X at
zero and going to L I could start it at
minus
l/2 and go to L
over2 put zero at the center here
nothing special about this it just
symmetrizes things nicely so that the
negative half and the positive half are
symmetric when you leave the space if
you're marching along and you come to L
over2 you pop back up at minus L over2
okay so we're taking a function a
periodic function e to the I KX and
integrating it from minus L /2 to
l/2 what is the answer okay first of all
what is the answer if K is equal to
zero
L this is L let's right is equal to l if
K is equal to zero and what if K is not
equal to
zero zero
because if you take a per a periodic
function that oscillates and you
integrate it then you get zero because
it's positive as much as it's negative
only for k equals z in that case of
course this doesn't oscillate it's just
equal to one then you get
L okay
so
uh now let's think of this as a function
of
K let's draw the K axis
let's draw the K axis here's the K
axis now K is not just any number it's
one of the allowed numbers so it's
discret does anybody remember what the
allowable values of
KR 2 pi n over L
right in particular as L gets bigger and
big bigger the distance between
neighboring values of K gets smaller and
smaller and eventually as L gets
infinitely big these discrete uh
intervals shrink to zero okay so now
what's the what's the
distance let's put k equals z k can be
positive or negative incidentally let's
put k equals z right over here here's k
equals
z all right what's the interval between
neighboring values of
k 2 pi over
L that's the distance from K = 0 or from
Nal 0 to Nal 1 for
example 2 Pi / L now let's take this
function this function is a function of
K of course we've integ I'm sorry I've
integrated it over
X it's only a function of K what is it
equal to Let's plot it on here it's
equal to
l when K is equal to Z so right at k
equals z here it's high and it's equal
to
l Let's
uh let's just give it
a a slight width just for the purpose of
drawing it just for the purpose of
drawing it right at k equal 0 here it
has a height equal to
l but at K not equal to Z it's zero
that's what we concluded at K it's equal
to l
if if K is equal to zero and it's equal
to zero if K is not equal to
zero so how high is it it's height L how
wide is it well one interval you can't
think of anything smaller than one
interval on here uh it has a width 2 pi
over L what's the area if I imagine
giving it that much of a width what is
the area under
it 2 pi so that means that this function
is 2 pi times the Delta function this
function here is 2
pi times Delta of K why Delta of K k at
k equals 0 it's not equal to zero at k
equal anything else it is equal to zero
now what is the meaning of this this is
the meaning of this is in the limit a
very very large
L this becomes a very very narrow very
very high function whose area is equal
to 2
pi okay we'll keep that in mind as we go
along this is called a direct Delta
function and we can now
say let's now go to the limit of very
large L if we go to the Limit a very
large l in other words we're making
these intervals progressively smaller
and smaller we're really approaching the
situation that really does Define the
direct Delta function then this integral
goes all the ways from minus
infinity to plus
infinity so just think of this as a
formal prescription for an integral of e
to the I KX and the rule is it gives
Delta of k 2 pi * Delta of K this is
equal to 2
pi times Delta of
K that's something of
importance that when you integrate over
a function of e to the I KX like this DX
you get a Chron uh a direct Delta
function of
K let's see if you can guess supposing
instead of doing the integration over X
I did it I did an integral over K
exactly the same integral except it's
not at all the same integral e to the I
KX but instead of integrating DX I
integrate
DK what must that be function of X it's
a function of
X but it's exactly the same structure
here except I just interchanged X and K
right X and K appear symmetrically here
so if I interchange X and K this doesn't
change but I've changed the integral
over X to an integral over K so this is
now some function of X but what is the
what is the
function 2 pi * Delta of
X so these are two little um
observations that we will see happening
we'll see they utility occurring in a
number of
places all right that's the direct Delta
function that's our first little bit of
mathematics
tonight the hell was
that next little bit of
mathematics I taught you what a cat is a
Kat is a symbolic notation for a Quantum
State I also think I told you you didn't
use the word I didn't what did I use I
did I did I did I did and I told you it
was half of a
bracket yeah okay it's the other half of
the bracket now that we want to talk
about the
bra otherwise known as
bra these are just notational devices in
for our purposes these are simply
notational devices and the question is
when do you use the bra and when do you
use the k for our purposes we will think
of
Kats as initial States in a process if a
process starting with some initial state
is described by some Quantum State we'll
describe the initial State as a k
Vector initial
in final States we will
describe
by bra vector and when you put a bra
Vector next to a k Vector you make a
bracket this is simply a bunch of
symbolic
manipulation but at the end what comes
out of the symbolic manipulations are
numbers okay numbers numbers
experimental
numbers so I'm going to teach you now
some symbolic uh
manipulations for
every let's go back to the harmonic
oscillator for the harmonic oscillator
we characterized the quantum states of
the harmonic oscillator by occupation
numbers
n the number of excitations of the
harmonic oscillator the number of times
number of units of energy that's been
put into the harmonic
oscillator we can also describe it
that's a k Vector that's the K
description of a particular Quantum
State we could also write it in terms of
a bra Vector so far I haven't told you
anything I just told you there's two
ways to write the same thing you say
What's the difference between them
not much okay but if we are clever in
our use of this notation it will help us
do some
bookkeeping that's
interesting all right now first of all
there's the notion of the inner product
between a bra vector and a c Vector now
all of this is in our past uh uh quantum
mechanics classes and I refer you back
to it we're going to go through it
lightning like tonight if I have a a k
Vector n and a bra Vector M I can put
them next to each
other and putting a k Vector next to a
bra Vector in this way always gives a
number the K vectors are abstract things
the bra vectors are abstract things but
the product of two of them back to back
or I don't know front to front I'm not
sure which in that form is a
number this
number now m stands for some Quantum
State the MTH Quantum state of the
oscill
and n stands for the nth state of the of
the oscillator this number this is
definition now is equal to
zero if n is not equal to
n and it's equal to one if m equals
n so the bra vector and the K Vector for
the same value of n have a product which
is one it's called the inner product the
inner product between these two it's 1
if n equals m it's zero if n is not
equal to M or to write it in a unified
form we can write it as Delta n m whose
definition is it's zero unless n equal m
and one if n is not equal to M it's kind
of like the direct Delta function it's a
discrete form of the direct Delta
function all right this is
notational this is just notational
tricks for things
now let's come to creation and
Annihilation operators what I want to
get at before we go further is how
creation and Annihilation operators act
on bra vectors I've told you how they
act on K vectors and I have not told you
how they act on bra vectors now of
course you can say of I haven't told you
in fact I haven't even told you the
rules which would allow you to deduce
how they
act but I'm going to show show you how
they act and then show you why this rule
was particularly nice all right so let's
take creation operators first of all
what does a creation operator
do when it acts on the nth Quantum state
of an
oscillator it multiplies it by square <
TK of n + 1 * the n + first
state what about the
annihilation the annihilation gives you
square of n *
nus1 so one of them raises the quantum
State one of them lowers the quantum
State and in each case they multiply by
the appropriate uh square root of
n now we can ask def now we're asking
for a definition this is not a theorem
which we want to prove this is a
definition of how creation and
Annihilation operators operate when they
act on bra vectors so how shall we take
a
A+ to act on the inth bra
vector and I'm going to tell you now
what the rule is the rule
is that however it acts on the nth
Vector it gives another Vector another
bra Vector of course let's Circle that
bra vector and now take its inner
product with the MK
Vector however this acts whatever it
gives it gives another bra Vector that's
the rule when an operator acts on a k
Vector it gives a k Vector when it acts
on a bra Vector it gives a bra vector
and the notation is such that when an
operator acts on a bra Vector you put
the operator to the right and hit it to
the left when it acts on a c Vector so
it's a neat notation the rule is that
you get exactly the same
answer as if you did
what a allow A+
to act on
M and then take the inner product within
see there's two distinct
operations however A+ should act on N
we'd like to find out how it should act
on N we're going to Define it so that
you get the same answer for this
bracket as if you allowed A+ to act on M
well I've given you the rule for how A+
acts on M and then take the inner
product with
n so let's see if we can figure out from
this from this set of abstract
principles or abstract definitions how
A+ act on
N let's
see let's first take the bottom line
here the bottom line let's calculate it
it's
n and now A+ acts on M what does that
give square root of n plus one that's a
number we take it outside side squ of n
+1 and then
what n +
1 what does this
give this this Factor gives zero unless
n is equal to n +
1 right if n is the same as n + 1 then
you get the number square root of n n +
one which also happens to be the square
root of n of
course so that's one way of calculating
what that's this over
here but notice it only gives an answer
a nonzero answer if this is one unit
higher than
this sorry yeah sorry it only gives an
answer if m is one unit lower than n if
m is one unit lower than M then A+ comes
along increases M by one unit and then
we get a non-zero answer so the only way
to get a non-zero answer is if m is one
unit lower than n well let's look at
this over here supposing that A+ acted
on N to raise
n then we would only get an answer if M
was one unit bigger than
n but according to this rule we only get
a non-zero answer if n is
one I think uh all right let me let me
say it let me say it accurately I get
my
okay from this form we see that n has to
be one unit bigger than M to get a
non-zero answer n must be one unit
bigger than M all right if on the other
hand a plus increase the value of n over
here then we would only get a nonzero
answer in the opposite situation where n
was one unit what less than M right so
this can't be the right rule that when
A+ acts to the left that it increases
the index here what it must do is
decrease the index
here and in fact that's the definition
that's the correct
definition
when
A+ acts on a bra Vector
n it doesn't increase in it decreases
in N minus one and what about the
numerical Factor there the correct
numerical factor is just square root of
n if you want it if you want you can
work this out all right what if it what
about N A minus what does that
do well the answer is is I've given you
enough rules that you can determine
yourself what it does what it does is it
increases n n + 1 * < TK of n + 1 in
other words to make the story
short when A+ acts on K vectors it
increases n and multiplies byun of n + 1
a minus decreases n and multiplies by
squ root of n when a plus and a minus
act on the bra vectors they just
interchange A+ decreases in and
multiplies by square otk of N A minus
increases n and multiplies byun of n +
1 that's the rule just that's the
rule which leads to a very lovely
calculus that's useful in quantum
mechanics so calculus meaning Now tricks
for computing simple things let me give
you an example let's calculate in two
distinct ways the following
quantity let's take A+ a minus remember
what that
was what do that stand for yes it stands
for it's the quantum mechanical operator
that stands for the occupation number
the number of Quant in the state and
let's
calculate this quantity
here A minus I'm
sorry A minus let's calculate it in two
different ways now for those who studied
some quantum mechanics you'll know that
this expression stands for the average
value of whatever this quantity is in
the quantum state in but for the moment
let's just calculate it as an abstract
exercise but let's calculated two ways
and the first way let's allow this
operator to act to the
right first a minus x to the right what
does a minus give when it acts on this
it gives Square < TK of
n time n minus
one we still have A+ which we haven't
used up
yet
n now numbers come on the outside
numbers like square root of n they come
on the outside square root of n
now what does A+ do when an acts on N
minus one pushes it back up it pushes it
back up and multiplies by
what one integer higher than what
appears here so that means again square
root of n that gives us two square roots
of n which means
n times n
what
n A+ on N minus one brings us back to n
and NN what is that that's just one so
it just gives us n if it acts A+ a minus
when sandwiched within the quantum state
in just gives us the numerical number
in what would happen if we did it in the
opposite not in the opposite order but
by acting to the left on the braa let's
do
it what happens when A+ acts on in to
the
left it gives us n
-1 * the < TK of
n but we still have to act with a
minus what does a minus do when it acts
on N minus one it raises you back
up raises you back up to n and gives you
another square root of
n so you see with this this definition
that the creation and
Annihilation or the raising and lowering
get interchanged when you
go to their action on bra vectors and K
vectors then it doesn't matter which way
you imagine these operators operate will
get the same answer that's a useful uh
useful
notation and so when you see a thing
like this you don't have to ask should
you operate with this to the right and
then take the inner product with the
left hand side or should you operate to
the left and then take the inner product
with the right hand side you get the
same answer that's the beauty of that
particular definition
here all right that's good now what are
we going to do with all of
this well of course we're going to study
Quantum fields which are objects built
built out of these creation and
Annihilation
operators uh yeah yeah let's let's go
right there let's go to the quantum
Fields go back to a qu simple Quantum
field that we've discussed
already and then come to the
description of quantum processes
scattering processes creation of
processes Annihilation processes and so
forth how they're described by Quantum
Fields or how they're described in terms
of mathematical Expressions involving
the quantum
Fields why are we interested in
processes like uh collisions and
creation and Annihilation processes
involving particles because in the
microscopic world that's about all we
can do if we want to do experiments the
only real handles we have on experiments
is colliding particles together and see
see what comes out and describe in those
processes how the initial state of the
particle of two particles for example
morphs into some other state involving
five seven nine particles four particles
whatever it
is uh the tool for that is quantum field
Theory and we're setting up some simple
examples all right so let's go back to
the definition of a Quant of the
simplest Quantum field the simplest
Quantum
field
we took it to be a function of only one
coordinate namely X there's no reason
why we can't think of X Y and Z
here and make position into a
three-dimensional thing if we do so
momentum also has to be oh incidentally
we'll work in units in which H bar is
equal to one I don't think tonight the
speed of light will come into anything
but what's the connection between
momentum and K if H bar was equal to
one they're the same normally you would
have an H bar over here H bar k but if H
bar is set equal to one K and momentum
are the same thing okay right okay so
we
concocted a thing which we call a
Quantum
field associated with the point of space
X as I said X could be a
three-dimensional point of space if it
is then K has to be
three-dimensional if we're living in
three dimensions then the momentum is
three-dimensional meaning to say it has
three
components and then K will also have
components but other than that the
formulas I'm going to write down are
pretty much the same in three dimensions
whatever number of Dimensions we're
doing so I have X was a sum over all the
allowed values of
momentum if we're talking about the
Universe on a circle or the periodic
Universe then these are the K's which
are 2 pi/ L * an integer if we're
talking about an infinitely Big Universe
then K can be any anything uh any number
sum of a
k summation of a k
of the creation operator for a particle
of momentum
K time eus I
KX that now has become a Quantum field
there's a conjugate Quantum field and
now we pretty much if we're uh quantum
mechanics people we talk about talk
about the hermiss conjugate if we're
classically oriented people we simply
talk about the complex conjugate we can
call it SAR or S dager of X the complex
conjugate which is a similar thing
involving Annihilation
operators time e to the plus I KX um
excuse me yeah is this a definition or
this is a
definition this is definition but you
know
definitions
the
question it's always appropriate when
somebody um uh gives you a definition to
say why is that the def definition right
and then the usual answer is wait wait
till you see how we use
it and you'll see that it's a useful
definition okay so I'm afraid that's the
situation here why is this the
definition because this is a useful
definition I could have put something
else here and it would have been a
useless definition
so it's it's premature to ask why this
is the definition but it is a it is a
nice simple expression it's not very
complicated sum over the allow allowable
values of
momentum creation operated times e to
Theus I KX or the complex conjugate
which has Annihilation operator time e
to plus I
KX now I'm going to do something even a
little bit
fancier okay I'm going to give these s
of x's some time
dependence so far they don't depend on
time the definition does involve does
not involve
time but I'm going to introduce some
time into the
game and how do I introduce time why do
I introduce time well
remember that there's a
connection between the momentum the the
wave vector k and the frequency of an
oscillation these are
Fields these are Fields Fields
oscillate as it's written now it doesn't
oscillate it doesn't have any time
dependence if this has anything to do
with a real field waves and so forth we
better introduce some time into it well
that's not so hard because we remember
that for each value of K there is a fre
frequency frequency tells us how things
change with time supposing I have an
object a mathematical
object which has a certain frequency
Omega how do I write the function that
goes that oscillates with frequency
Omega e e to the I Omega t e to the I
Omega T which also happens of course to
be cosine Omega t + I sin Omega
T this is a function with a definite
frequency the frequency is
Omega all right
now in past lectures I pointed out to
you that for various kinds of
waves
each k k is a wave Vector it's inversely
related to the wave length for each k
there is a frequency so we can say that
there is for each K there is an Omega of
K and each oscillation each time we see
an e to the minus I
KX we can put in front of it an
oscillation in front of it or behind it
an e to the I Omega of K time
T now this thing has not only space
dependence but it has time
dependence and moreover it's time
dependent we do the same thing here of
course e to the minus I Omega of K
T Let's uh let's erase uh side dagger
for the moment we'll come back to it I
want more room on the
Blackboard here's an
object which has both space dependence
and time
dependence the time dependence has been
arranged in such a way that for each
value of the
wavelength or k it oscillates with a
Time dependence which is just the right
time dependence for that
wavelength this is now a function of
space and time it truly is a Quantum
field now it varies in space and
time okay I want to take an example and
show you that in the
example there is an
equation a wave equation for S of x and
t and see if we can figure out what the
wave equation
is see if we can find the wave equation
for S of x and t knowing the connection
between Omega and K now I haven't told
you what the connection between Omega
and K is right but let's suppose that
we're talking about non relativistic
particle in other words I'm not talking
about a
photon I'm talking about a species of
particle which moves with much less than
the speed of
light it uh we're working in the
approximation in which everything is
non-relativistic
okay when H bar is equal to one let's
put it over here H bar equals 1 Omega
has another name what's the other name
for
Omega
energy
remember energy of a photon or energy of
a Quantum of a single Quantum we're
talking about a single Quantum now the
energy is H bar Omega if H bar is equal
to one Omega and energy are the same
momentum is equal to H *
K so when when H bar is equal to one
energy is frequency and momentum is is
wave
number okay what's the connection for a
slowly moving particle slowly means only
slowly moving compared to the speed of
light what's the connection between
energy and
momentum right energy of a slowly moving
particle is the square of the momentum
divided by twice the
mass this is of course the same thing as
writing energy is equal to 12 mv^ 2 and
P is equal to
MV all right if we uh if we solve for V
and plug it in into here we get this
relationship here okay that also tells
us now the relation between Omega and
K k^2 over 2
m
right
so
now we really do
know the precise form of s of x and
t it's a sum over the allowed values of
momentum and Omega of K is not just some
arbitrary Omega of K but it is k^2 over
2m with that
Proviso s of x and t solves or satisfies
a differential equation a wave equation
let's see if we can see what the wave
equation
is first of all in wave equations
derivatives with respect to space and
time enter and are equal to each other
in some form that's what a wave equation
is equations for how space variation is
related or how time variation is related
to space variation so let's consider
first the time derivative of s what's
the time derivative of s I'm going to
call it s dot standard notation for time
derivative side dot we get we obtain by
just differentiating the time dependence
with respect to T that's equal to sum on
K A+ of k e to Theus I
KX times what times I
Omega inside the
summation I Omega of
k e to the I Omega of K T all I've done
is say every time this is still under
the summation here every time I
differentiate with respect to T it pulls
down a factor of I
Omega right so that's side
dot now let's look at the space
derivatives what is the space derivative
decide by d
x well we do exactly the same thing
every time we differentiate with respect
to X it pulls down a factor of minus i
k okay so this is equal to the same kind
of thing summation of minus i
k A+ of
K time e to Theus I KX e to the I
Omega of K
T so differentiating with respect to X
always just pulls down a factor of ik K
differentiating with respect to time
pulls down a factor of I
Omega now there's no simple relationship
between this and this why not because
Omega is related to k s if Omega was
simply related to K for example if Omega
had to be equal to k then we would just
say s dot is equal to D DX for example
imagine a world or a kind of particle
where the frequency is in fact equal to
K that's a very simple situation in that
situation I Omega K is the same as Min
uh
is apart from a minus sign is the same
as ik K and we would just say
that such a field satisfies a equation
that s dot is equal I think to minus DC
by DX is that clear yes all right but
that's not the case here we have to have
omega equals k^2 so how can we get
K2 take take another derivative each
time we differentiate it brings down a
factor of ik K so let's differentiate
again that brings us minus i k 2 what's
minus I k^ 2 I think that's minus k^ 2
right minus k^
minus with a minus
sign but
now k^2 is 2 m *
Omega k^2 is 2 m *
Omega so Let's
uh write that 2 m *
Omega and let's divide the left hand
side by 2 m 2 m is just a number excuse
me yeah uh I'm confused is the minus
sign really supposed to be there I
thought you had minus
I uh let's see let's check when I
differentiated with respect to time it
gave I Omega so that's our I Omega now
when I differentiated with respect to K
it gave a minus i k and I did it twice
so that gives minus i
k
squared what is minus i k
2us k 2 this is minus k
2 so yes as far as I can tell the minus
sign is there
okay the there was a there was a minus
k^ 2 and then I substituted for minus k^
2 - 2 m
Omega and that's where this came
from okay I'm more familiar with this uh
in the form in which we divide both
sides by 2 m this doesn't matter of
course let's divide it by 2 m and we get
1 / 2
m time the second derivative of s with
respect to space
squared is Omega time all this stuff but
that's clearly proportional to side dot
what's the what's the
relationship you got an iega there here
we have an yeah we better let's let's
yeah there's going to be an i in the
formula uh we can divide by I which is
the same as multiplying by minus
I okay to make a long story short the
right equation should be minus
i s dot that's the time derivative of
s divided or is equal to 1 / 2
m times the second derivative of s with
respect to x^ SAR now do I have the sign
right or not pro of course I don't I
never get it
right okay now is it
right no you had it
[Laughter]
right I'm not
sure one over 2 N then not one over 2 N
squ one over 2 N one over two M okay uh
let's see is the minus sign there or not
let's put a minus here and then there's
a plus here so it looks like this it
looks like it's the plus sign far as I
can tell it's the plus sign yeah well
it's just you have on the opp side
ofation I so well of course that will do
the that will do the trick
right okay does anybody know the name of
that equation it's the schinger equation
right but it's not the Schrodinger
equation for the same thing as an
Elementary quantum mechanics in
elementary quantum mechanics
s is just a function of position it's
not an operator it doesn't uh do things
it's just a thing whose square is a
probability here it is an operator when
it acts on States it creates particles
it annihilates
particles this is an instance of the
relationship between particles and
Quantum
Fields Quantum fields are operators they
happen to have the same equations as the
schinger equation of Elementary quantum
mechanics they are very closely related
but they're quantum mechanical operators
they're
observables you can observe them under
what circumstances do they behave like
classical fields in other words you can
measure them and the same way you
measure the electron magnetic field the
answer is that they behave like
classical Fields when the number of
quanta is very large when the number of
Quant is large then the magnitudes of
the fields are large and the quantum
fluctuations are small the quantum
uncertainties are small exactly like a
harmonic oscillator a harmonic
oscillator if it's got a big motion
behaves classically if it's only got one
Quantum unit of excitation it behaves
very Quantum
mechanically so this is an example as I
said of a Quantum field and it has
creation and Annihilation operators in
it nevertheless it's a thing which
satisfies an equation and the equation
is the Schrodinger
equation uh this is obviously a more
advanced notion of the Schrodinger wave
function than just saying it's a thing
whose square is the probability for a
given particle it's something uh uh a
little bit
different okay and as I said it is a
Quantum field it's the simplest version
of a Quantum
field
uh how do we use
it how do we use it to describe
processes so I'm going to give you an
and we've already talked about this a
little bit what I didn't talk about
which I want to come to now is energy
and momentum
conservation and how energy and momentum
conservation are codified or codified
whatever the right word is in the
various dependences of Sai and the way
that we describe various processes I
want to I want to imagine now describing
the very very simplest
process in which a particle scatters off
a
Target the Target in this case
is a thing which is so heavy that it
doesn't
recoil a particle comes and either
reflects off it or scatters off
it in three dimensions it could have its
trajectory changed in other words it
could be coming in from the left and go
off uh straight
ahead but what can you
say about a particle scattering off an
ordinary Target a Target that's just
stuck there it doesn't move stays there
forever and
ever which of the conservation laws
would you expect to be true for that
particle how about
momentum just a moment
got yes of
course got ref retion reflection and
what's that ref refle reflection
refraction and
absorption well let's forget absorption
for the moment all right the particle
comes in and goes out so it's not
absorbed but yes it could be reflected
bing bang it could be refracted in which
case its direction of motion has
changed in any case the momentum of that
particle generally is not the same
coming in as going out of course
secretly what happens is momentum is
really conserved but what happens is of
course the target absorbs some of the
momentum but let's just fix the target
let's imagine nailing down the Target
and the target is not part of our
mathematical description or the motion
of the target is not part of our
mathematical
description then in the mathematical
description of a particle scattering off
a Target the momentum of the particle is
not
conserved all right what about the
energy yeah the energy of the particle
is conserved if you take a tennis ball
well a tennis ball is a bad example
because it uh you know it heats up when
you throw it against the wall but an
idealized tennis ball where you can
ignore
heat you throw it against the wall and
it bounces off what can you say about
the way that it bounces off you can't
say the momentum is conserved the
momentum has gone from that direction to
that direction but the energy is
conserved
so how can we see can we
see uh that in some simple model of the
scattering process that momentum is not
conserved and energy is conserved
using these wave
Fields so we talked about this last time
a little bit and I showed you how you
could
describe a
process of scattering creation
Annihilation and so forth using these
Quantum Fields so here is
a model here here is
a space is horizontal time is vertical
and the axis over here represents a
Target it's it's fixed in
space it neither and it goes on and on
forever into the past it just sits there
and a particle comes
in it hits the target at some
point and either bounces off or goes
forward or scatters into some other
direction so we describe the initial
state by saying there's one
particle with a momentum
K let's call it K in for initial initial
or
incoming and then a particle goes off
having scattered off the
Target and let's use a language now it's
absorbed by the Target and suddenly
reemitted by the Target okay think of it
instead of just thinking of it as
bouncing off the target let's in the
back of our mind have a picture in which
it is absorbed or annihilated by the
Target and then
instantaneously recreated by the Target
but possibly with a different
momentum let's call that final
momentum K final let's just call it Ki
and
KF
initial and final and what are we
interested in we're interested in the
probability amplitude the quantum
mechanical probability
amplitude that the particle
scatters from momentum K initial to K
final now one more
ingredient I'm going to assume that the
scattering can happen with equal
strength equal at any time all always at
the same place we're going to place the
target at xal
0 but we're going to assume that the
scattering process can occur at any time
whatever time that particle gets
there it will scatter or not scatter or
do whatever it does but with no special
dependence on the time at which the
process takes place that's going to be
our our basic assumption how do we
describe
the event of the particle being absorbed
at position x equals
zero well we describe that by
means this should be side dagger
shouldn't
it I think this should be sorry dagger
it's the daggers are that go with the
plus signs here I think in my notation
that I used last time uh I think that's
right but then e either plus I say I
don't think so um I think a plus always
went with a minus here I think so uh and
then this one would be plus if I
remember okay we describe it in the
following by by a kind of bookkeeping
it's it's all bookkeeping but it's
useful bookkeeping
you absorb the
particle this is a piece this is a field
which creates particles let's write
down the
other
conjugate field which annihilates
particles it's the complex conjugate or
S of X
andt which is made up out of
annihilation
operators e to the plus I KX e to the
minus I Omega of K T it's just the every
place everything is conjugated e to
Theus I KX becomes e to plus I KX and so
so forth and these are to be thought of
as complex conjugates of each other or
hermiss conjugates of each other all
right let's imagine first of all
absorbing the particle at the origin how
do we do
that we absorb it by an operate well we
start with the initial State the initial
state has no particles with any
particular momentum except one particle
with momentum Ki
so if we described it in terms of
occupation numbers
only the occupation number associated
with momentum Ki would be non zero we
can also just label that by saying
there's one particle with momentum Ki
and be done with it we don't need to
specify all the particles that aren't
there but nevertheless it's useful to
keep in mind that when we specify the
initial state with specifying all of the
occupation numbers of all the various
quanta and only one of them according to
assumption here is present so there's a
one here and all the others are zero and
we just label it by saying well there's
one particle with momentum
Ki then that particle is
either is annihilated at the origin if
it's if it's at the origin and let's
describe that by
S of x and t but X is equal to
zero Zer and T why is x equal Z I'm
assuming that if the process happens it
happens at the Target and the target is
at xal 0 but it can happen at any time
so that's the process of absorbing the
particle at time
T that's what this says but then when
the particle is immediately
recreated that's a why you say why does
it have to be it doesn't have to be
that's the model that I'm making a
particle absorbed and immediately
reemitted
that's a mathematical model it's not
necessarily a law of nature about uh any
particular kind of particle in fact in
the real world a photon can be absorbed
by an atom and emitted later or earlier
so what we're talking about here is a
simple mathematical model in which the
process happens all at an instant
particle absorbed and reeni and
reemitted and what's the emission
described by it's described by the
creation of a particle also at point
zero so that's side
dager of zero and the same time
t but what time what time should I put
there the same time but which time
matter it will
matter
so why why one or zero how about let's
say it can happen at anytime anytime
that the particle gets
there okay whenever the particle gets
there that's the same as
saying integrate this over all possible
times in other words there is a process
in which the particle AB is absorbed at
this time at this time at this time and
so forth so let's not Prejudice what
time it happens by just averaging or
integrating over all possible
times this is a mathematical expression
which we can work
out I will show you as we go along what
the implications of this integral over
time are but the basic physics of it is
that the process could happen at any
time
no special time no particular time is
singled out as
special and we get rid of the
specialness of the value of time by just
integrating of all values of
time okay what does this give this gives
the final State here's an initial State
these are operators which operate on the
initial State and give some final
State how do we calculate the
probability that the final State
consists of one and only one particle
moving with some other
[Music]
momentum all right if you remember your
rules of quantum
mechanics we take the inner
product of this state with the final
state so let's say one particle with
momentum kfal
this is a number remember a c Vector
operator bra Vector give us some kind of
number is this number the probability
for the
scattering not quite probably Square we
have to square it we have to take the
absolute value of it and square
it now I've left out one important
ingredient in this expression we're
going to evaluate this we're we're going
to go through it and we're going to see
what it says
the course
I'm I'm purposefully um or not
purposefully I would rather be able to
explain all of this in complete logical
order but you know given an hour to do
all of quantum field Theory we have to
draw on things that we've done in the
past so when the last I explained that
probabilities are squares of amplitudes
and amplitudes are inner products
between initial States and final States
okay so here's the thing we want to
calculate but I've left one thing out
I've left out the strength of the
scatterer the strength of the scatterer
is a measure of the strength of
interaction between the scatterer and
the and the scattery so let me give you
an example you could have a Charged
particle at the origin which is
scattering a photon a photon comes in is
absorbed by the scatterer and reemitted
what is in that case what corresponds to
the strength of the scatterer the answer
is the electric charge of the
charge the bigger the electric charge
the more probable it is that the
electron that the photon will get
scattered there is a measure of the
strength of the interaction between
scatterer and Scattered particle the
strength of the coupling between them uh
which uh which has to be codified
somehow and it is simply by a numerical
number put here it's called the coupling
constant g g for what I don't know what
G is for it's a measure of the strength
of the coupling or the strength of the
interaction between the
scatterer and between the scatterer or
the Target and the particle
itself
um I'll give an example some
examples the scattering of a Meson from
a proton is a strong
process meaning to say that if the Meson
is absorbed if the Meson arrives at the
location of the proton it has a high
probability of scattering that's
indicated by a large coupling
constant a photon in the vicinity of a
charg also could be a proton a photon is
also absorbed and reemitted by a proton
the probability for that scattering the
probability that the photon gets
redirected is much smaller than the
probability for the Meson and that's
indicated by the coupling constant being
much smaller for the interaction of a
charge particle with a you think of
something even
smaller yeah a neutrino interacting with
a proton has an even smaller constant
for scattering off this that's what
made be also for an
electron well for the Target being an
electron or the well right now we're
just right now we're just making a model
in fact of an electron or something like
an electron scattering off a Target so
this is don't think of this as being
valid for any real thing this is a
simplified model for for a number of
different
situations what about the scattering of
a
graviton by a uh by a nucleus graviton
is the analog for gravity of a
photon well it can happen but it's an
extremely small constant I won't even
try to tell you how 10 to the minus some
large number by comparison all right so
the strength of the of the inter action
and the probability that this actually
happens that the particle gets
redirected is indicated or or
described by the coefficient G which
appears here it's just a number and it's
called the coupling constant what's
called a coupling constant there are
many coupling
constants all right so let's see if we
can calculate
this what are we trying to calculate
we're trying to calculate the
probability for going
from K initial to K final that's all
Yeah question
question is there any logic for G being
a constant as opposed to being a
function of Omega or k h that's a good
question the answer is there is no logic
to
it no there is logic to it but um there
are situations where it's a function of
Omega all right I we'll I'll show you
some situations
ation as I said this is a model of a
particular kind of simple scattering
there are more complicated kinds of
scattering a more complicated kind would
be and this would really be for the case
of a photon and an atom for example
Photon comes in atom gets
excited and then de exites by emitting
the
photon okay here there's a little Gap a
Time gap between the time the photon has
absorbed the time it's
emitted this happens to be equivalent to
saying that the coupling constant is
Omega
dependent okay so um as I said we're
talking about a simple model and just
trying to find what the
consequences what the consequences are
there's going to be one important
consequence and it is very general the
rest is not so General but the one
important consequence uh that I want to
get to
so let's just plug
away we're going
to
just go straight
ahead plugging in for Sai its value
written in terms of creation and
Annihilation operators and then use
those creation and Annihilation
operators to annihilate the initial
particle and recreate the final particle
and
calculate the expression that's up there
the square of it will be the probability
so let's do it okay so yeah
gity be
one if G is equal to
one yeah all right um that's a good
question well you could ask what happens
if G is much bigger than one does that
mean that the probability is much bigger
than one no it doesn't it doesn't it
just means that you have to go ahead
into a more comp complicated calculation
this calculation that I'm doing is
only correct for very small
G okay it's correct for very small G
what you have to do when G is
larger is extremely interesting and will
be very important to us in what follows
the answer is you have to do higher
order perturbation Theory okay but we're
not doing that now well we're just doing
the simplest thing all right so let's do
the simplest thing and just plug in for
S its value
all right s the first s not the S diager
but the first
s is a summation over K not K initial
but just k a summation index a minus to
absorb the initial particle of
k e to the I
KX e to the minus I Omega sub K T and
that acts on the initial state which
happens to have one particle of momentum
Ki
yeah thank
you X is
zero at the scatterer so let's leave it
out e to the I k0 is just
one
okay which terms in this sum will
contribute
only when K is equal to KI will we get
anything
right why because the annihilation
operators give zero when they act on
states where there are no particles the
only particle around has momentum
Ki and so only when K is equal to KI do
we get anything but nevertheless let's
leave it in this form just for the
moment now what about the other operator
side dagger that's also a sum over
momentum I better use a different
index because I don't want to use the
same summation index twice uh and get
confused so I'll call it let's call it
l and now we put A+ of
L that creates the new particle with
momentum L
times e to the well X is still equal to
zero
X is still equal to zero so we don't get
anything from here but then we have e to
the
I Omega sub L *
T what about the final State the final
state is the state with a particle of
momentum K
final okay which term all right first of
all the term in the sum of a k which
contribute
is only when k equals Ki right what
about the sum here over l what does l
have to
equal K final remember that when A+ acts
to the left it annihilates it has to
find a particle to
annihilate A+ of L only gives you
something when L is equal to kfal so
really both of these sums
collapse only k equal K initial and Lal
K final that's all there is what do I
leave out
G okay but I've also left out something
else where is
it integral
DT it's the integral
DT which is the thing that I'm really
interested in all right so the
only contributor here
is k equal
Ki what does a minus of ki do when it
acts on a state with momentum
Ki it just creates a state with no
particles right it annihilates the
particle with momentum
Ki what about this sum this sum is only
nonzero when L is equal to kfal so we
can put kfal here
and when this acts on a state with kfal
oh sorry yeah okay right we're okay this
is
good all right what happens when a acts
on the state with K
initial it just gives is a state with no
particles right so that's just no
particles what happens when this acts on
a state with particle with momentum
kfal it just gives no particles
again what is this
number one so that much is one so all
this Opera nonsense of creating and
annihilating particles all goes away and
all we have is a number
G that's the probability for the
scattering or that's the amplitude for
the scattering G nothing else except
that we have this
integral not in this
expression I think you're thinking about
a relativistic
problem no no no there was only one
particle
here because there was was only one
particle yeah yeah there was only one
particle right okay but the important
thing the real only thing that really
I'm illustrating here is the integral
over time and what is it it's an
integral
DT e to the I Omega let's just call it
final minus Omega initial this is K
initial time
t
that's the whole upshot the time
integration gives us an integral over e
to the I Omega final minus Omega initial
T all of the operator nonsense just
gives us a one nothing very interesting
the coupling constant gives us a g and
now we have to evaluate this
integral what is this
integral Delta function this is an
example of the Delta function
an integral DT of e to the I something *
T let's see was it 2 pi * a Delta
function if I
remember I think it was 2
pi
G
times Delta of Omega final minus Omega
initial does this ring a bell Delta of
Omega final minus Omega
initial it's only nonzero when Omega
final is equal to Omega initial Omega
final is the final energy Omega initial
is the initial
energy so somehow magically now notice
that if we had not integrated over time
we would not have
gotten this Delta function of
energy so somehow there's a connection
between the fact that uh that there's a
conservation of energy and the fact that
it doesn't that there's no preference
for any specified
time we could have made a model in which
the scattering only happens if uh if the
time is within some boundaries then this
integral would have only gone over some
limited amount of time it would not have
made a Delta function so the ingredient
here which is closely connected with uh
with energy cont
obervation is time translation symmetry
that every time is like every other time
yeah that whole thing is square that
matter ude oh oh the square of the Delta
function
well yeah yeah yeah the probability for
the probability we have to square this
this is the probability
amplitude the probability itself will
have the square of this but who cares
about the square of a Delta function
function the Delta square of a Delta
function is also zero if Omega final is
not equal to we have to worry about
squares of Delta functions but in any
case this will be zero unless the
initial energy is the same as the final
energy let's assume the initial energy
is the same as the final energy then
this is the operative important part of
the scattering amplitude let's call this
by its name it's a scattering amplitude
and the probability for the scattering
is proportional to 4 pi^ 2 g^
2 right the strength of the scatterer or
the probability for it to scatter
contains G squar they always wind up
containing pies but the important thing
is the G squ and
which Which F which final momenta can
happen well I didn't specify anything
special about the final momentum here
this final momentum could have have been
anything as long as the energy was the
same so this scatter has the property
that it takes a
particle and with a probability
proportional to
G2 changes its momentum with equal
probability to any momentum with the
same
energy that's it so this is a scatterer
which can scatter into any Direction
with equal
probability okay any Direction with
equal
probability that of course is not true
of all scatterers this is this very
simple model that scatters with all with
equal probability in all
directions and
the coefficient g^ 2 4 pi^ 2 g^ 2 in
this case is the probability so this is
I've I've shown you many things so far
tonight in particular the definition of
a coupling constant the the fact that
the integration over time is the thing
which ensures energy
conservation which is just another way
of saying the problem has time
translation
symmetry there was nothing spe special
picked out about one time or another
time and uh and I've Illustrated the
idea of a scattering amplitude or the
amplitude the thing which becomes
squared in order to calculate a
probability
this
um is a fairly generic set of
ideas but the spe the details can differ
yeah can you always simplify these
things by by redefining the positions to
X zero say l can you always simplify
this by redefining the position so X is
zero yeah uh good question
question uh yes yes in this particular
case yes the question of what would
happen had you not put x equal zero here
right that's that's kind of the question
okay what you would have found is there
would have been another Factor the other
factor in
here would have been in the amplitude e
to the i k initial minus
kfal
times the position of the scatterer what
should I call the position of the
scatterer
just let's just call it X of the
scatterer X of the
target X of a Target is a number X of a
Target is just the position of the
target when the position of the target
was zero this didn't occur if the target
was moved over to position X Target you
would get an extra Factor but what would
happen to the
probability no change because the when
you square meaning to say when you
multiply by the complex conjugate this
goes away multiplying this by its own
complex conjugate which is what I mean
by
squaring multiplying by its own complex
conjugate this goes away so this does
not appear in the
probability get the same probability no
matter where the target is but in an
intermediate stage of calculation and
calculating the um the amplitude the
position of the target would
occur okay yeah so it's a very uh simple
model so you can cramm two years into an
hour yeah but the mathematics unless I
see it wrong seems to say if we uh said
that it didn't matter where it happened
but it happened exactly at times zero
we'd get a different conservation yes
what would you guess conservation would
be well it's momentum and momentum and
no energy conservation right right and
does that have a physical interpretation
or is this more a property than just a
mathema well of course in the real world
if we studying for example the
interaction of two particles and we take
everything into account both particles
and so forth the scattering can occur at
any time at any
place right uh but you could imagine you
can certainly imagine an approximate
situation where you might okay you're
asking me is there ever a situation
where here the approximation was we just
ignored The Recoil of the target okay
and therefore the momentum was not
conserved is there ever a situation
where energy is not
conserved and that sort of situation is
what happens when you have time
dependence in the coupling or time
dependence in the strength of
interaction now yes there C certainly
are situations where that can be a good
approximation to say something something
makes a sudden change in the system from
the outside and when a sudden change in
the system happens that's when the
scattering takes place yes we can think
of situations where that happens I can
where we can we can try to concoct one I
can't right now I'm a little too fuzzy
but yes we can certainly concoct a
situation where something sudden happens
in such a way that it makes the
scattering possible at an instant of
time and then energy would be completely
not
conserved do most of the coupling
constants come from experimental data
also you just said introducing a Time
dependence in the coupling constants
which start well that usually means when
there's a Time dependence in the
coupling constant that usually means
there something that you've ignored in
the system which is either moving or
time dependent something whose dynamic
and degrees of freedom you're sort of
ignoring in the same way that you
ignored the possible recoil or
repositioning of the target here
so uh I will I'll try to think of a
situation where um
where there's an interesting uh
violation of energy conservation or
where the bookkeeping was such that you
threw some of the energy away but let's
come back to it
yeah hitting a moving Target hitting a
moving Target right hitting a moving
Target is an example where the target
where the where again the motion of the
target is thought of as completely fixed
yes
right
and on a um on certain scales you have
to worry about the size of the target
versus the the um the frequency of the
the size of the wave yes so electon
versus xray versus gamma versus yeah
here in this model the target the size
of the target was
Zero yeah in this right and you're
absolutely right something interesting
happens when the target has a certain
finite size and we can we can discuss
that but let me just come back to the
question about the moving uh the moving
Target if you think about it for a
minute of course if you have a moving
Target energy is not conserved for
example supposing that wall was moving
toward me and I had a tennis ball and
all of a sudden the wall hits the ball
and the ball moves off the energy of the
of the tennis ball we're not accounting
for the energy of the Moving Wall we're
not trying to worry about that so if the
wall is moving that corresponds to a
Time dependence in this case a Time
dependence not of the coupling constant
but in a Time dependence of the location
of the scatterer that would be enough to
make energy not conserved and we could
see it uh in the uh in the mathematical
formalism okay so to reiterate these
creation and Annihilation operators are
the tools which allow you to discuss
transitions of particles from one state
to another
state um we have not talked
about well actually we did talk about
creation and
Annihilation
um
yeah let's
uh let's discuss another situ
situation oh incidentally
supposing
s was the field operator for an
electron each kind of particle has its
own separate
field okay so electrons have a different
field than photons when you put s here
you better specify what particle you're
talking about okay um let's think of the
electron s describes electrons
now here was a process in which an
electron came in and an electron came
went
out what happened to the total charge
did the total charge
change no one particle came in one
particle come out now let's imagine a
different situation let's imagine a
situation where one electron comes in
and two electrons go out okay crazy I
mean it can't happen but let's for the
moment nevertheless try to imagine it
how might we describe it by the same
kind of
mathematics one electron comes in two
electrons go out how do I modify this
and here my simple model is two
electrons go out from exactly the same
point yeah we might put
another we might Square this in other
words s of 0 t s Dagger of 0 t s Dagger
of 0 t
t s of 0
t Okay oops there should be a t here
right
yeah
okay what about now this is this of
course can't happen in nature because
electric charge is conserved this
corresponds to the annihilation of one
electron in the creation of two bad idea
but nevertheless let's write it down
what about two electrons in and two
electrons out is that
okay well at least it doesn't violate
electric charge conservation how would
we describe
that another
s SII SII side dagger side
dagger how about two electrons in three
electrons
out s s s side dagger side dagger side
dagger okay which ones of these are
allowed and what's the rule I'm not
deriving a rule now we're just going to
observe a
rule same number of equation and
Annihilation right same number of size
as side
daggers this is not
allowed this is allowed this is not
allowed rule is same number of sides as
side diag is there another way to
express
that the order
matter the order of the operators it's
not a question of the order of the
operators it's the number of sides
versus the number of side
daggers when the number of sides all
right
let's when the number of
size is different than the number of
size
daggers versus when the number of sze is
the same as the number of side
daggers how can you
diagnose these combinations of course
it's it's very easy just to count the
number of sides and side daggers of
course but let me give you a
mathematical
diagnostic that uh really does have a
deep meaning let's imagine a
transformation now s dagger does mean
the complex conjugate of
Sai it is the hermiss conjugate in the
language of quantum mechanics but the
Herm Mission conjugate is the analog of
qu of complex conjugate let me imagine
that I take an expression like this just
a mathematical expression like
this and I transform
s by multiplying it by a phase a phase
means an e to the I time some number
let's call it Alpha Time
s I just I'm just doing now blindly uh
playing a game wherever I see S I
multiply it by e to the I Alpha Time s
what happens to side
dagger If I multiply a complex quantity
by e to the I Alpha what happens to its
complex
conjugate e to the minus I Alpha side
dagger what happens to objects that have
an equal number of S and S
dagger they stay the same what happens
to objects which don't have an equal
number of s and side
dagger they change so we could
characterize the allowed processes by
the ones which are described by
operators which are invariant unchanged
by the operation of changing the phase
of the operator now that
H indeed but uh for the moment let's
give it a simpler name invariance under
changing under redefining the field so
that you change its phase overall
everybody you change the phase by a
constant phase
Factor if the
description
if the
interaction expression here is
invariant then charge is conserved if it
is not invariant then charge is not
conserved what happens supposing I had S
Plus s
dagger what kind of thing does that
correspond to
incidentally all right I'll leave that
you to think about but is this is this
unchanged by
phase no no no is that the real part
this is the real part of s and if you
multiply by a phase you change the real
part of s so that's not a quantity which
is
invariant question if you have a Target
and you have an electron imp pinching on
a Target you may have a many secondary
electron
emitted yes well wait if you have what
kind of Target a Target full of
electrons yeah well sure you can have
yes yes yes yeah right ah you say what
happens if you have an
atom and you hit the atom with an
electron and 75 electrons go off well
charge is not not violated of course
what has happened is the atom has
changed all right all right this is a
situation in which you cannot get away
with ignoring the Dynamics of the Target
in the particular the the important
dynamics of the target Target is the
change of charge of the target you can't
in this case treat the target as though
it was a completely passive thing you've
got to remember right
uh what's that the target change yes
that means the target itself has to be
described by a Quantum
field right and we we can discuss that I
think uh we've gone far enough for
tonight all right so what do we found we
found that time translation invariance
corresponds to energy conservation phase
invariance we can call this phase
invariance corresponds to charge
conservation and we haven't worked it
out yet we will work it out next time
that spatial translation in variance
corresponds to momentum conservation
I'll show you how that works next time
but we're making our way slowly into how
particle physics processes are described
by fields that's our goal for the for
the next uh one more lecture on it I
don't know maybe half a lecture on it
and then we'll move into some of the
symmetries and some of the more
interesting uh laws of particle physics
just hav work out in the MTH but we
could have just easily had a process
that was dagger dagger dagger yes yes
but it's not hard to re okay right
that's correct I've I've chosen always
to put all the daggers to the left and
the size to the right remind me next
time and I'll show you how to rearrange
other Expressions so that they become
like
this I know what you're asking you're
asking what would happen if instead of
this we put si side dagger si side
dagger and I will tell you next time but
they still match but they still match
this is allowed mean same no not quite
not quite not quite not quite remind me
next time I'm too tired now to start uh
going into it
but uh remind me absolutely next time
what is the difference between this and
this and I'll show you next
time all right I I left I actually left
time for some questions if you want to
ask some questions I just have run out
of steam in the
in well it's not that yeah go
ahead have you that um that in
vares charging VAR well it's it's sort
of trivial if you have as many sides as
side diagoras that means the interaction
eats the same number of electrons as it
spits
out all right each s annihilates an
electron each side dagger creates an
electron you know Pro that pH variance
implies Char charge conation the other
way
around all I did was point out that all
of the objects with equal number numbers
of size and side
daggers will be invariant under the
phase operation here if they have
different numbers of size and side
daggers let's take a case sigh side
dagger side
dagger you get it right I'm not sure
what the rest of the question is if they
have equal numbers of size and side
daggers it's phase and variant and it
conserves charge if it has different
numbers of sides and side daggers it's
it's not phase invariant and it doesn't
uh conserve
charge so we're just
observing that when it's phas invariant
it conserves charge when it's not phas
invariant it
doesn't there are two other
r two other rules at the same time
conservation energy momentum in charge
for the moment we haven't we haven't
gone through momentum conservation
although it was mentioned by somebody
here asked me if the process can happen
at any place instead of any time then
yes then it conserves
momentum but we'll come to it we'll do
that
case yeah In classical mechanics it's
n's
theorem in quantum
mechanics it's even simpler but
uh
uh but um here I'm sort of short
circuiting all of that discussion by
just showing you how it works
mechanically in uh in terms of these
Quantum
Fields um up there to the probability of
that first system is uh 4 pi^ 2 G2 does
that mean when you
empirically assign a value to the comp
constant that it must be less than 1
over 2 pi in that particular case yeah
it must be less than one over something
or you have or your model is very
incomplete if you ask me in what way
it's incomplete I will tell you in what
way it's
incomplete is that the real scattering
process is not described by just a
particle coming in and getting scattered
out it's described by something more
complicated which is a sum of prob a sum
of amplitudes in which the particle
comes in
scatters off the target comes in goes
back out comes back in scatters off the
target twice comes back in scatters off
the target three times it's a whole
infinite series each one each term has a
factor of g g in front of it uh it's
only when G is
small that only the first term is
important but we'll come to that this is
this is a basic theme that when the
coupling constant is small you can get
get away with the simplest minimal
process when the coupling constant gets
large one has to well let's just call it
what it is one has to sum up an infinite
number of finding
graphs basically these pictures that
I've drawn are Fineman graphs and the
vertices of the Fineman graphs are
described by these
operators okay the vertices of the fan
diagrams tell you the basic elements
that can happen
particle comes in bounces back out
that's side time side dagger two
particles come in and bounce back out
that's s dagger side dagger s s or
whatever and we'll
we'll give things their proper name next
time
uh yeah are there any situations when
coupling constant has imaginary
component well
uh
yes what time they
um you want you you want me
to the existence of a Theta parameter in
qcd the existence of a Theta parameter
in qcd I'm sure that means nothing to
you yeah it it does happen that there
are complex values of a of coupling
constants it usually means the time
reversal invariance has been broken
complex coupling constants are usually
an indication of a violation of um of
time reversal invariance that's really
what it comes down to now you can't see
that from what I've told you up till now
at least if you can you're smarter than
I am uh I can see it but only because I
know how to see it but it's not obvious
but that is the case complex coupling
constants mean that time reversal and
variance is uh is is is broken in other
words things don't look the if you run
the process backward as a movie going
backward it's not a possible
process yes um you said at one point
also that instead of having the um the
uh scattering occur the outgoing
particle at the same time as the in
particle would be before or after you
also mentioned before not happen not now
but yeah no no I did say that and I sort
of regretted it the minute I said
it but we we will we will
H Frank no this is it's a fair question
but it's not the time for it now yeah
Jean Franklin used to say it last before
you tickle it what's that Jean Franklin
would say it lasts before you tickle
it
okay you're probably going to say you'll
get to this at some point but how would
how do you turn this into something
that's
relativistic
ah again you're jumping way ahead I'm
trying to go
slowly and everybody's pushing me to get
ahead okay I you really want to know you
add this and this and put a square root
of Omega K in the
denominator no no this
we're jumping ahead I mean uh and
uh yeah hey you uh talked about charge
conservation conservation conservation
with that phase
Factor but the rest mass
m that doesn't change also in the during
the in a non-relativistic process but in
a relativistic process it
can and there's nothing in basic quantum
mechanics mechanics which says that rest
Mass can't change uh it's a combination
of quantum mechanics or not even quantum
mechanics even just classical mechanics
together with an invariance principle
and the invariance principle is Galilean
invariance which I which is an analog of
uh non-relativistic analog of lorensen
variants um but yeah it it is true in
non-relativistic uh situation total mass
can't change but can in relativistic um
uh
scattering so what did you want to ask
me exactly
well it's just that logically we think
of rest Mass conservation in the same
terms as charge no no no no no no no not
at all not at all one is absolutely true
in nature the other is only true for
very very slow
velocities right there's nothing sacred
in physics about the conservation of
rest mass and once more is not true um
an electron and a positron annihilate
into two photons there's no conservation
of mass there is a conservation of
electric
charge so one of them is a sort of
accidental non-relativistic uh fact the
other is a deep underlying uh uh
symmetry of nature which happens in
simple case just to correspond to this
um phas invariance next we'll talk about
Fons we'll talk about what happens if
you have more than one species of
particle supposing you have electrons
and muons and quarks and so forth how do
you describe all of this what's allowed
what's not allowed what kind of
processes and uh all in the language of
quantum FS yeah strictly speaking with
your scatterer example you gave us you
said it was an electron but I thought we
only knew about boson so far ah good
point good point good point good point
yes yes yes yes good
point yeah this so we have um we're
talking about a bosonic version of an
electron yeah sorry I completely missed
that you're right right but there are
particles in nature which carry electric
charge yeah right exactly um a Charged
pon a slowly moving charged peson would
be an example of a bon which you would
describe in this way yeah yeah so
good absolutely
right thank
you for more please visit us at
stanford.edu